Guide to the William Wildschut Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
William Wildschut papers
1878-1927
WA MSS S-2386
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
1.93
(3 boxes)
Photographs, writings, clippings, and other material related to Wildschut's study of North American Indians. Includes 64 photographs, most of them portraits of Native Americans, primarily Crow Indians, including Plenty Coups and Two Leggings. Other photographs are of encampments, ceremonies, medicine bundles and other objects, the grave of Two Leggings, cavalrymen at the monument at Little Bighorn, and Wildschut handing Marshal Ferdinand Foch a portrait of Plenty Coups. There are eleven short typescript essays and a set of manuscript notes on Native American customs, and four letters vouching for Two Belly (Crow Indian chief) while hunting, signed by four different Indian agents, one of them Nelson Appleton Miles.
Wildschut, William, 1883-1955
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William P. Wreden on the William Robertson Coe Fund, 1976.
Conditions Governing Access
Box 3: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
WILLIAM WILDSCHUT
William Wildschut, an ethnologist and field researcher for the Museum of the American Indian, was born in the Netherlands. He was the author of Crow Indian Beadwork (New York: Museum of the American Indian, Heye Foundation: 1959), and Crow Indian Medicine Bundles (New York: Museum of the American Indian, Heye Foundation: 1960). His biography of Two Leggings, a Crow Indian chief, was published in 1967, twelve years after Wildschut's death.
Scope and Contents
The Papers consist of photographs writings, clippings, and other material related to Wildschut's study of North American Indians. Series I, Photographs, includes 64 photographs, most of them portraits of Native Americans, primarily Crow Indians, including Plenty Coups and Two Leggings. Other photographs are of encampments, ceremonies, medicine bundles and other objects, the grave of Two Leggings, cavalrymen at the monument at Little Bighorn, and Wildschut handing Marshal Ferdinand Foch a portrait of Plenty Coups. Series II, Writings, includes eleven short typescript essays and a set of manuscript notes on Native American customs. Series III, Other Papers, contains four letters vouching for Two Belly (Crow Indian chief) while hunting, signed by four different Indian agents (one of them Nelson Appleton Miles), and clippings. Oversize, box 2, contains material from Series I, and is organized in box order.
Crow Indians -- Pictorial works; Crow Indians -- Social life and customs; Indians of North America -- Pictorial works; Indians of North America -- Social life and customs; Little Bighorn, Battle of the, Mont., 1876 -- Monuments -- Pictorial works; Photographic prints; Plenty Coups, Chief of the Crows, 1848-1932; Two Leggings, approximately 1847-1923; Foch, Ferdinand, 1851-1929; Miles, Nelson Appleton, 1839-1925; Wildschut, William, 1883-1955
- Photographs, n.d.; Series I; 0.15; (.33 box)
  Scope and Contents
  Series I, Photographs, is arranged into three subseries: Portraits (Native Americans, Others), Native American Scenes and Objects, and Other Photographs. The photographs are arranged alphabetically by caption title.
  - PORTRAITS
    - Native Americans
      - "Curly." Three portraits, n.d.
        "Copyright 31 Wildschut" and "Copyright 133 Wildschut" at bottom right of two of the photographs
      - "John Wallace, Crow Indian" (Box 1, Folder 1)
      - Miller, F. E., Hardin. "Hoop in the Forehead", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 2)
      - "Plenty Coups", n.d.
        "Copyright 119 Wildschut" at bottom right corner of photograph
      - "Plenty Coups & Daughter" [and a second photograph of the daughter]. Two handcolored photographs
        "Copyright 116 Wildschut" and "Copyright 118 Wildschut" at bottom right corner of photographs
      - "Sees the Living Bull. Crow Indian Chief, Medicine Father of Two Leggings." Two photographs of same image
      - [Empty mat for "Shot in the Hand Crow Indian]
        Mat signed by Wildschut
      - "Two Leggings. Crow Indian Chief"
      - [Unidentified man, bare-chested], n.d.
      - [Unidentified men], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 3)
      - [Unidentified old man wearing large feather headdress], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 4)
      - [Unidentified woman with two children.] Handcolored
        "Copyright 115 Wildschut"
    - Others
      - "Buffalo Bill Reproduced after a painting 1904", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 5)
      - [Buffalo Bill on a white horse], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 6)
      - Howard, Photo. "Group of Officers, Fort McKinney, Wyoming.", n.d.
      - "Marshall Foch receives my picture of Plenty Coos W. Wildschut", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 7)
      - O'Neill Photo Co. "Pres Coolidge After Becoming Chief Leading Eagle. Days of 76. Deadwood, S.D., n.d. (Box 1, Folder 8)
      - "Tom LaFarge & self on the Crow Indian reservation" (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - NATIVE AMERICAN SCENES AND OBJECTS
    - [Crow medicine pipe bundle and sundance bundle] (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - "Fort Fetterman - Wyoming By Lacom, 1873." Photograph of a painting [on a tent?] Two photographs of the same image, n.d.
    - [Native American camps, portraits of Native Americans in front of tipis, with portrait of Two Leggings when younger, women raising tipi.] 12 photographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Numbered 101-130, with gaps
    - [Native American ceremony, witnesses, and camp.] 10 photographs
    - [Native American ethnographic objects.] 7 photographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Numbered D14-D29, with gaps
    - [Photoreproduction of a two page, partial description of the life of Native Americans, with drawings of camp and Native Americans on the trail] (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - [Tipi in a camp painted with a large eagle], n.d. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - "Two Leggings Grave Nr Hardin Montana", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - [Two tipis, one painted with warriors on horses.], n.d.
      "Copyright 151 W. Wildschut, Billings, Montana." Mat signed by Wildschut
  - OTHER PHOTOGRAPHS
    - [Little Big Horn monument, with cavalry in front of it.] 5 photographs, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Photoreproduction of "Sweetwater Station Idh. Ter." by C. W. Collins, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Writings, n.d.; Series II; 0.15; (.33 box)
  Series II, Writings, is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - "Arapaho Specimen No A-312...Arapaho Medicine Mirror." Carbon typescript, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - "Blackfeet Pipe Bundles." Carbon typescript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - "Crow Sweattipi Ceremony," "Crow Miniature Sweattipi Ceremony," and "Crow Tanning Process." Carbon typescripts with pen-and-ink diagram on "Crow Sweattipi Ceremony" (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - "The Kicksetti Totem and The Kahl-Teen Totem." Typescript (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - "Secret Rites of the North-American Indians." Typescript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 22)
    With first page of later draft
  - "Shoshone Indian Sundance." Carbon typescript (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - "Some Points on the American Indian and His Religion." Typescript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - "The Trading Post." Typescript, corrected, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - "Use of skull bundle on the war-path." Carbon typescript, corrected (Box 1, Folder 26)
    "Informant: Coyote-Runs"
  - Holograph manuscript notes on Native American customs, with drawings of objects by Wildschut, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 27)
- Other Papers, 1878-1927; Series III; 0.1; (.33 box)
  - 4 ALS vouching for Two Belly, Crow Indian chief, while hunting - one letter signed by Nelson Appleton Miles, 1878-83 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Clippings mentioning William Wildschut, 1923, 1927 (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Clippings on Crow Indians, 1923, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Clippings on Native American culture, 1923, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Empty envelope from Chapple Drug Co., Billings, Montana labeled "Duplicate Scenic pictures", n.d. (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Oversize, 1.33; (1 box)
  Oversize contains materials from series I, and is arranged in box order.
  - "Curly." Three portraits (in Series I), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - "Plenty Coups" (in Series I), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - "Plenty Coups & Daughter" [and a second photograph of the daughter]. Two handcolored photographs (in Series I) (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - "Sees the Living Bull. Crow Indian Chief, Medicine Father of Two Leggings." Two photographs of same image (in Series I) (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - [Empty mat for "Shot in the Hand Crow Indian] (in Series I) (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - "Two Leggings. Crow Indian Chief" (in Series I) (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - [Unidentified man, bare-chested] (in Series I), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - [Unidentified woman with two children.] Handcolored (in Series I) (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Howard, Photo. "Group of Officers, Fort McKinney, Wyoming" (in Series I), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - "Fort Fetterman - Wyoming By Lacom, 1873." Photograph of a painting [on a tent?] Two photographs of the same image (in Series I), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - [Native American ceremony, witnesses, and camp.] 10 photographs (in Series I) (Box 2, Folder 43-45)
  - [Two tipis, one painted with warriors on horses] (in Series I), n.d. (Box 2, Folder 46)
- Restricted Fragile Papers
  Conditions Governing Access
  Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
  - Box 1, folder 18 (Box 3, Folder 47)
  - Box 1, folder 19 (Box 3, Folder 48)
  - Box 1, folder 20 (Box 3, Folder 49)
  - Box 1, folder 23 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  - Box 1, folder 26 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  - Box 1, folder 29 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Box 1, folder 30 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - Box 1, folder 31 (Box 3, Folder 54)